This דף daf is ע"ד, Ayin Dalet, 74 and we'll pick up
again at the very bottom of ע"ג עמוד ב'. Ayin Gimmel Amud
Bet. Alright, so we had this whole ענין inyan in the משנה
Mishna can a שיתוף shittuf work in the place of an עירוב
eruv or an עירוב eruv again, not just individual courtyard but courtyards
together in the place of a שיתוף, shittuf, the משנה Mishna actually
seemed to say an asymmetry, a שיתוף shittuf can work instead of
an עירוב eruv but not an עירוב eruv for a שיתוף shittuf
and there's a certain logic to that because the עירוב eruv of
the courtyards does not directly address incorporate the מבוי. maboi. Nevertheless, the
גמרא gemara did not buy into that asymmetry and tried to work
it out either according to רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir or according to
the רבנן. Rabbanan. Then we move to the statement of רב Rav
that רב Rav says the משנה Mishna was talking that the courtyards
did not open one into the other. The courtyards were separate from
each other. That might have been to solve this problem why the
עירוב eruv doesn't substitute for the שיתוף shittuf but the גמרא gemara
turns it onto a different issue and it says first it starts
with a thought that you had to convey the שיתוף shittuf from
one courtyard to the next via the מבוי, maboi, they dropped that,
and then the last thing it says is no no no this
is going to this question about when can you suffice with just
a לחי lechi or קורה kora for your fourth wall for a
מבוי. maboi. Normally we require four walls for a מבוי maboi the
Rabbis were lenient and required just a לחי lechi or קורה, kora,
a vertical or horizontal beam. But only if it has the official
status of a מבוי maboi which is normally defined as two חצרות
chatzerot and each חצר chatzer having at least two houses. So two
houses make it a חצר chatzer and two חצרות chatzerot make it
a מבוי. maboi. And that's what you need. So that רב Rav's
point was that if the courtyards open into one another and in
theory they could all create one עירוב, eruv, then that fact that
they could
unify makes it considered one חצר chatzer and not two and therefore
prevents this leniency of the לחי lechi or קורה. kora. So that's
what we pick up with now at the very bottom of ע"ג
עמוד ב'. Ayin Gimmel Amud Bet. גופא. gufa.
So let's see what we said before: אמר רב, amar Rav, אין
מבוי ניתר בלחי וקורה, ein maboi nitar belechi vekora, a מבוי maboi
cannot be made permissible with a לחי lechi or a קורה, kora,
top of ע"ד עמוד א', Ayin Dalet Amud Aleph, עד שיהיו בתים
וחצרות פתוחים לתוכו, ad sheyihiyu batim vechatzerot petuchim letocho, unless you have
houses and courtyards, which means two houses in each courtyard and two
courtyards opening into it. And that defines it as a מבוי maboi
that the Rabbis were lenient to allow a לחי lechi or a
קורה. kora. ושמואל אמר אפילו בית אחד וחצר אחת. uShmuel amar afilu
bayit echad vechatzer achat.
Even one house and one courtyard. Now what does that mean? Either
or? Does it mean one house by itself and just a yard
by itself? So רש"י Rashi says it means one house opens directly
into the מבוי maboi and a courtyard opens into the מבוי, maboi,
but of course for it to be defined as a courtyard it
has to have at least a house attached to it. So
it's so
whereas according to רב, Rav, right here's your מבוי maboi and here's
your courtyards and each courtyard has two houses,
right? According to שמואל, Shmuel, that's רב, Rav, according to שמואל, Shmuel,
you've got there's your מבוי, maboi, you have one house that opens
directly and one courtyard and that courtyard
contains
at least one house.
So they're willing to define it as a courtyard with just one
house and he really
doesn't need two courtyards, it's just one courtyard and one house together.
You don't see it. I mean there's a lot that's not being
said. So I'm telling you how רש"י Rashi interprets
it. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן אפילו חורבה, Amar Rebbe Yochanan afilu horva,
even a sort of like
a desolate like a field, a ruin, right,
like an unbuilt-up lot or a
ruin. So not just one house. So again what רש"י Rashi adds
is that רש"י Rashi assumes you have
to have at least one חצר. chatzer. So רש"י Rashi assumes what
we're debating is what can be on the other side. According to
רש"י Rashi what רבי יוחנן
Rebbe Yochanan is saying is it doesn't even have to be a
house, it can even be a חורבה. horva. But of course this
isn't in the text, but רש"י Rashi is assuming that everybody agrees
to a חצר. chatzer. רב Rav requires two חצרות chatzerot and each
one having two houses. שמואל Shmuel and רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan first
of all say that a חצר chatzer can be one house and
then they're debating how much what's the minimum you can have on
the other side. That's the way רש"י Rashi is trying to explain
it. There's no question there are probably two dozen other ways of
reading what exactly is being said. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara. So אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, amar leh Abaye leRav
Yosef, so אביי Abaye said to רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, אמר רבי
יוחנן אפילו בישיא של כרמים? amar Rebbe Yochanan afilu bieshia shel keramim?
What about instead of this ruin you had like this lot, this
unbuilt lot, you had like this path leading into the vineyards? Let's
say you had even something even less. I mean if you need
almost nothing, maybe even something
that's a forest, a path in a forest. So the גמרא gemara
says אמר ליה לא, amar leh lo, לא אמר רבי יוחנן אלא
בחורבה. lo amar Rebbe Yochanan ela behorva. No
no no let's not go overboard. He limited it to a ruin
or like a desolate lot דחזי לדירה dechazi ledira that in theory
you could build that up and you could live there. And put
a house in that lot. But אבל שביל של כרמים דלא חזי
לדירה, Aval shevil shel kramim delo chazi ledira, something like just a
path in the middle of a vineyard that isn't fit for for
being built up and for habitation, לא, lo, he would not say
it. Okay. אמר רב הונא בר חיננא ואזדא רב יוחנן לטעמיה, Amar
Rav Huna bar Chinana veazda Rav Yochanan letaimei, Rabbi Yochanan goes according
to his reasoning that he's sort of lenient here in terms of
what defines a מבוי mavoi for a לחי lechi and קורה. kora.
דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishna, רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi
Shimon omer, instead of אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון
אומר אחד גגות ואחד קרפיפות ואחד חצירות רשות אחת הן לכלים ששבתו
לתוכן ולא לכלים ששבתו בתוך הבית. Rabbi Shimon omer echad gagot veechad
karpifot veechad chatzeirot reshut achat hein lekeilim sheshavtu letochan velo lekeilim sheshavtu
betoch habayit. This is a statement we've had before,
but it's worth taking a minute and sort of explaining it and
also explaining it in the context of everything we've learned until now
because it's a point that could be easily lost. When we say
that you need an עירוב eiruv for a חצר. chatzer. Okay, here's
your חצר, chatzer, here are all your houses, you need an עירוב.
eiruv. What happens if you don't have an עירוב? eiruv? Where can
you carry if you don't have an עירוב? eiruv? You have your
individual houses and can you carry in the courtyard?
No, because these things were there before Shabbat.
So if they start here before Shabbat, you can't carry in it,
okay? Because the basic point is this is a רשות היחיד, reshut
hayachid, these are רשויות היחיד, reshuyot hayachid, they're just different רשויות היחיד,
reshuyot hayachid, okay? So you know, we're going to name A, B,
C, D, E, F, so and this is G. You can't carry
from one רשות reshut into another, okay? You go ahead and you
make an עירוב eiruv and making it all A because in theory
if you didn't have to go through the courtyard, you know, they're
all the same type of רשות reshut anyway. But whatever. Anyway, so
the problem is going from one type of רשות reshut into another.
You make an עירוב eiruv and all of a sudden this becomes
one big C and it's all the same רשות reshut and you
can carry, you know, from here to here and from here to
here and so on, okay? But even without the עירוב, eiruv, you
could carry obviously in each house and you could even carry stuff
that started in the courtyard within the courtyard. But a כלי kli
defines its identity, right? Again, it's not who's doing the carrying, whether
it's you or a stranger, it doesn't matter. A כלי kli that
started here, a vessel that started here, you can't take it out
of your house into the courtyard, from the courtyard into the house,
but if it started in the courtyard, you can carry it in
the courtyard. The issue is going from one domain to another. So
comes along רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says,
let's say I have a couple of courtyards, or I don't know,
do it like this or something, or it doesn't matter, a couple
of courtyards, well, it depends how they're bounded then. Anyway, fine, we'll
do it like this. You've got a couple of courtyards,
okay? And these courtyards open into one another and have not made
an עירוב eiruv with one another. Okay? So normally all along we've
been assuming since they all have their houses, okay, all along we've
been assuming that if they haven't made an עירוב eiruv with one
another, right, you can't carry from courtyard A into B into C,
correct? If they haven't made an עירוב. eiruv. Comes along רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says I disagree. You can't
carry from a house of A into A if A hasn't made
an עירוב, eiruv, or if A hasn't made an עירוב eiruv with
B, you can't carry from a house of A into B because
they're different. But these are all courtyards and the same way you
could carry from one house to another without an עירוב eiruv if
you didn't have to go through a courtyard, if houses had a
window between them, you could go from one house to another, he
says these are all courtyards and therefore if a כלי kli starts
in, you know, A1, A2, A3, if it starts in A3, you
can carry it to A2 or to A1. You can't carry it
into one of those houses, but those are all conceptually one big
unit, okay? So the same way, the point being and again it's
a little confusing, but it's worth reiterating because it's really essential to
everything we've been talking about, the issue is not the courtyard carrying
in the courtyard per se, the issue is carrying from one type
of רשות היחיד reshut hayachid into a different type of רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid unless they've been made into a unit. So comes along
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he says, so these are all the same
effective רשויות היחיד reshuyot hayachid and therefore if a כלי kli starts
in one, you can carry to the other without an עירוב, eiruv,
okay? So let's read that again.
So you say you can carry from
one מבוי mavoi to another? What? Can you carry from one מבוי
mavoi to another? No, מבוי mavoi he wouldn't say, but מבוי mavoi
is more of a public domain anyway. So let's take a look.
He says אחד גגות, echad gagot, whether you're dealing with with roofs,
okay? ואחד קרפיפות, veechad karpifot,
or whether you're dealing with a קרפף karpeif which is like an
enclosed lot. ואחד חצירות, veechad chatzeirot,
or whether you're dealing with courtyards, רשות אחת הן, reshut achat hein,
they are considered one domain, לכלים ששבתו לתוכן, lekeilim sheshavtu letochan, vessels
that started in them, ולא לכלים ששבתו בתוך הבית, velo lekeilim sheshavtu
betoch habayit, but not a vessel that started in the house. So
the same thing by courtyard, right, if you had like roofs, you
know, whatever, distinct houses and you want to carry from one roof
to the next, you know, roofs. Roofs are all considered also to
be one type of a domain, and if you had like these
empty lots or whatever, and they were קרפיפות karpeifot and they opened,
all these types of things, they don't need a special, they don't
need a special עירוב. eruv. They're all one domain and they're all
one רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. The biggest חידוש chiddush is the חצר
chatzer because since we know that you need an individual עירוב eruv
for each חצר chatzer and you need an עירוב eruv to carry
from the house of a חצר chatzer into the חצר, chatzer, you
would have thought and and you need an עירוב eruv from one
to the next, and he's saying no, if the vessel started in
one חצר, chatzer, it's all one domain and you can carry it
into, wait, wait,
we need an עירוב eruv was like A2 is pouring it, but
A3 set it out, right, you can still carry from רשות reshus
to רשות reshus from A1 to A3
from a vessel that started in A1, you can't carry from a
house of A1 to A3. Yes.
So if two of them made an עירוב eruv and the other
one didn't want to join, right, like they're not like excluding themselves.
Right.
Okay, now, now, right, now, one minute, let me just, one
minute.
Right,
now רש"י Rashi actually points out that he actually even goes further
than that, and he actually says that you can carry from rooftop
A, rooftop in A1 to rooftop in A2, and from rooftop in
A2, you can carry into A2 itself, that basically that
חצר, chatzer, קרפף, karpaf, and גג gag are all are all essentially
one big domain because they're all places that are not actual places
of inhabitation themselves, they're not actual homes. So they are conceptually one
big domain, so you can actually carry not just for a כלי
kli that started in A1, not just from A1 to A2 and
from A2 to A3, but you can go up to a rooftop
of A3, and if there's a big backyard here and a קרפף,
karpaf, you can go into that. All of those things are one
domain even without an עירוב. eruv. Yes.
That is not obvious from the this text.
Right. I know, and that's actually debated later on. There are some
that agree that each subcategory is its own unit, but not that
it's one big, you know, one big abstract category. Okay, so this
is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, quite a lenient position about what you
can do without an עירוב. eruv.
So let's, yes, and
they would have to be adjacent, and they would have to be
adjacent. Yeah, they'd have to be adjacent because then the question is,
I mean, then it's just, you know, you can't go through like
a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim to get from one to the other.
You have to always be in a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. This
is dealing with only the rabbinic issue of even if it's all
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, they have to be the same genre,
you know, they can't be different types of רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
But obviously, if you have to cross a street to get from
one to the other, we're not talking about that. We're talking about
they're all right adjacent. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so that's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
אמר רב הלכה כרבי שמעון, amar Rav halacha k'Rabbi Shimon, we rule
like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay, still not clear what this has
to do with this issue about בתים
וחצרות. batim v'chatzeros. והוא שלא עירבו, v'hu shelo eirvu, and that's only
though if they didn't make an עירוב. eruv. Listen to the irony.
אבל עירבו גזרינן דאתי לאפוקי מאני דבתים לחצר. aval eirvu gazrinan d'masi
l'afokei manei d'batim l'chatzer. If however they made an עירוב, eruv, then
you cannot. Wait, hold on one second, I just want to double
check רש"י Rashi one minute.
Right, not an עירוב eruv together. He says, when can I carry,
and this is now going to become confusing again.
He says
A1, A2, A3, okay, and then you have all the homes. When
can I carry? He says from
A1
to A3, something that starts in in the courtyard of A1, only
if A1 has not made an עירוב. eruv. Why? Because as soon
as A1 makes an עירוב, eruv, what are they going to do?
They're going to take from the house into the חצר. chatzer. That's
okay, but then they're going to take from the חצר chatzer into
the extra חצר, chatzer, which is not okay. Right, an A כלי,
kli, right, can go from any A to any A, but if
you make an עירוב eruv here, we'll call the houses B's, okay,
and the עירוב eruv is a C. So now if they stay
within the C zone, you can go from the house here, but
it's not, it's not a courtyard כלי, kli, right, so you're not
able to go from the house to the courtyard and from the
courtyard to another courtyard. It's now an עירוב eruv כלי. kli. Right,
it's an עירוב eruv כלי. kli. Okay, so this only works if
it starts in the courtyard. As soon as you make an עירוב,
eruv, you're going to take stuff from the house to the courtyard,
which is okay in that courtyard, but that עירוב eruv doesn't doesn't
help with this and therefore you're we're afraid you'll come to take
from the house to the courtyard and the courtyard to another to
another courtyard.
Okay, yes, rooftops, קרפיפות, karpeifot, and חצרות chatzeros are three separate entities,
or you can take from roof to,
no, so that's what I said before, it's not clear from רבי
שמעון's Rabbi Shimon statement, but actually, and the גמרא Gemara explores this
later on, he considers them all one big entity.
You can take from
a roof to a חצר. chatzer. Yeah, if it started in one,
yeah. Okay, so now the, so that's what רב Rav says. ושמואל
אמר בין עירבו בין לא עירבו. VeShmuel amar bein eirvu bein lo
eirvu. No, it doesn't matter whether they did or didn't make an
עירוב; eruv; we're going to let you—you can't go from house in
A to A and from there A1 and from A1 to A2,
that we agree you can't do—but we're not going to make a
גזירה. gezeirah. We're going to say that even if A1 made an
עירוב, eruv, you can still go from the courtyard of A, something
that started in the courtyard of A1, to an A3. בין עירבו
בין לא עירבו. Bein eirvu bein lo eirvu. וכן אמר רבי יוחנן
הלכה כרבי שמעון בין עירבו בין לא עירבו. Vechein amar Rabbi Yochanan
halacha k'Rabbi Shimon bein eirvu bein lo eirvu.
Now what the heck does that have to do with the question
about בתים בחצרות? batim b'chatzeiros? Well, when—about how do you define a
מבוי, mavoi, right? That seems unrelated to how you define a מבוי.
mavoi. It's a completely separate debate about do you make a גזירה
gezeirah when you can carry from one courtyard to another, you know,
that that would be more problematic if that courtyard made an עירוב.
eruv. Yeah, about
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan paskin—I'm sorry, right—רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan paskin that
you don't need בתים בחצרות. batim b'chatzeiros. But still, how is it
related? So the גמרא Gemara says, what, so okay, but still not
clear. Let's look what the גמרא Gemara says. אלמא, Alma, says the
גמרא, Gemara, לא גזרינן דילמא אתי לאפוקי מאני דבתים לחצר. lo gazrinan
dilma ati l'apukei mani de'batim l'chatzer. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
not concerned that if A1 makes an עירוב, eruv, we're going to
say, "Oh, now they'll come to take it from their house into
their courtyard and from that courtyard into another." He doesn't make that
גזירה. gezeirah. הכא נמי, Hacha nami, here too, לא גזרינן דילמא אתי
לאפוקי מאני דחצר לחורבה. lo gazrinan dilma ati l'apukei mani de'chatzer l'chorva.
We're not concerned that if we allow this thing to be a
מבוי, mavoi, you're going to take from the courtyard—remember, we were back
at this statement? You have your מבוי mavoi
and here's your חצר chatzer with one house, and here's your—or חצר
chatzer and חורבה chorva both start with a ח. ches. Okay, sort
of like meat and milk. So anyway, so he says, גמרא Gemara
interestingly until now it seemed, and that's why there's a huge תוספות,
Tosafot, because the גמרא's Gemara's taking like a real change of tack
here. Until now it seemed the question was a formalistic one: do
we define this as a מבוי mavoi if it only has one
חצר? chatzer? How—how many houses do you need for a חצר? chatzer?
How many חצרות chatzeros do you need for a מבוי? mavoi? Just
a formalistic definition. But now the גמרא's Gemara's saying is there's another
concern. The concern is that even if we consider this a מבוי,
mavoi, right, what might you come to do? Nobody is living in
this חורבה. chorva. You're not making an עירוב eruv or שיתוף מבואות
shituf mevo'os with the חורבה. chorva. Okay, nobody is living there. Okay,
but that means that it remains actually considered to be a separate
zone, a zone that actually is not one with the people here.
So if we allow you to sort of, you know, carry, you
know, into here, you might come to carry from the מבוי mavoi
into the חורבה. chorva. That's the concern. That should be the concern
for רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So you see, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
isn't concerned about those types of things, that he says, and that's
why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going according to his reasoning. Of
course, it's funny, okay, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't make a
גזירה, gezeirah, fine, but that didn't get to the basic debate. The
basic issue did not seem to be about a גזירה. gezeirah. But
anyway, that's how the גמרא's Gemara's kind of getting it. Yes.
How—how is a חורבה chorva defined? Because in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
there's hardly a square inch that hasn't been settled at some point.
I don't know what to say. I don't know what to say,
but I do want to, by the way, point out the irony.
Why can you go from the חצר chatzer to the מבוי, mavoi,
right? There's also no שיתוף. shituf. So here's the irony. The irony
is since no one is living in the חורבה, chorva, you don't
need a שיתוף. shituf. There's only one person in this entire back
street, so he doesn't need a שיתוף. shituf. But because this חורבה
chorva is not part of an עירוב eruv and it's conceptually a
different type of a space, right, like חצר chatzer is different from
בית bayis and גג gag and קרפף karpaf and so on, so
even—so therefore you cannot actually carry, you can carry into the מבוי
mavoi but you can't actually carry into the חורבה. chorva. So therefore
the גמרא Gemara says, "Ah, that's not a problem for רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, he's not concerned that you'll come from—to—from doing one to
doing the other."
Yes. But the מבוי mavoi still requires a לחי? lechi?
The מבוי—and mavoi the מבוי—but mavoi a לחי lechi is enough because
we defined it as a לחי, lechi, a לחי lechi is enough.
Okay, so let's keep on going. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: יתיב רב
ברונא וקאמר להא שמעתא. Yasiv Rav Bruna v'ka'amar l'hai shma'tsa. רב ברונא
Rav Bruna was sitting and telling over this discussion of שמואל Shmuel
that says that even a house and a courtyard you don't need
two courtyards and two houses. Okay, going back to the earlier point.
אמרי ליה Amrei leih רבי אלעזר בר בי רב, Rabbi Elazar bar
Bei Rav, אמר—so amar רבי אלעזר בר בי רב Rabbi Elazar bar
Bei Rav of the house of רב Rav said, אמר שמואל הכי?
amar Shmuel hachi? Did שמואל Shmuel really say this? אמר ליה אין.
Amar leih in. Yes. אמר ליה אחוי לי אושפיזיה. Amar leih achvei
li ushpizeih. Show me where he's staying. I gotta ask him this.
I don't believe he said this. אחוי ליה. Achvei leih. He showed
him. אתא לקמיה דשמואל. Ata lekamei de'Shmuel. He came to שמואל. Shmuel.
אמר ליה אמר מר הכי? Amar leih amar mar hachi? Did you
really say this? אמר ליה אין. Amar leih in. Yes. So he
says, אמר הוא דאמר, amar hu d'amar, but the master said, you
said, אין לנו בעירובין אלא כלשון משנתנו. ein lanu b'eiruvin ela k'lashon
mishnateinu. We are limited—we go exactly by the language of the משנה.
mishnah. You might remember we said this once before. The question is
which משנה mishnah was he referring to. Now which משנה mishnah does
he think שמואל Shmuel meant? The משנה mishnah that says—our משנה mishnah
from
yesterday—שהמבוי לחצרות כחצר לבתים. she'hamavoi l'chatzeros k'chatzer l'batim. Right, it's the—you know,
you know what did they call those on the SATs? A is
to B as B is to C? Analogies. Analogies. Not a syllogism.
Anyway, so a מבוי mavoi is to the courtyards as the courtyard
is to the houses. Right? Units of houses make up, are needed
for a courtyard, and the units of the courtyard make up a
מבוי maboi or make up the sort of collective of the שיתוף
מבוי. shituf maboi. And therefore what's the relevance of that? They're all
set in the plural. So חצרות chatzerot are למבוי. le-maboi. So a
מבוי maboi needs two חצרות. chatzerot. And בתים batim is לחצר. le-chatzer.
So a חצר chatzer needs two בתים. batim. So you should have
said like רב Rav that to be called a חצר chatzer you
need two houses, and to be called a מבוי maboi you need
two חצרות. chatzerot. Okay, so how do you say one and one?
So the גמרא Gemara says אישתיק, ishtik, he was silent. So קיבלה
מיניה או לא קיבלה מיניה? kiblah minei o lo kiblah minei? Did
he accept the retort or not? Meaning did he reverse his position
or not based on this קשיא. kashya. תא שמע, ta shema, come
and hear. דההוא מבוי דהוה דייר ביה איבו בר איחי. de-hahu maboi
de-hava dayyer beih Eivu bar Ichi. So there's a certain מבוי maboi
that this person by the name of איבו בר איחי Eivu bar
Ichi was living in it.
עבד ליה לחי abad leih lechi ושרא ליה שמואל, ve-shara leih Shmuel,
שמואל Shmuel said it's permissible. Now we can assume here that he
basically had a just you know one חצר chatzer and one בית.
bayit. Okay and that's or that's at least what we're thinking. And
that's going to be the issue. Did he allow that to be
considered a מבוי maboi that one לחי lechi is enough? So אתא
רבנא, ata Rabana, so came רבנא, Rabana, שדייה, shadyei, he threw down
the לחי. lechi. He said what? You can't do this! This doesn't
have two חצרות! chatzerot! So he threw that down.
Remember they were trying
to, yeah right, they did it in the בי ריש גלותא bei
reish galuta and one of them was undoing the others. Okay אמר,
amar, okay so now the poor guy who had asked שמואל Shmuel
for a פסק, psak, who was it? איבו בר איחי. Eivu bar
Ichi. So he said מבוי דדיירינא ביה ועשינא משמיה דמר שמואל, maboi
de-dayyerina beih va-asainah mishmeih de-mar Shmuel, the מבוי maboi that I live
in and I've been you know going back and forth and carrying
in and out in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. ניתי רבנא בר
רב נשדייה? neiti Rabana bar Rav nishdyeih? So this guy רבנא בר
רב Rabana bar Rav is going to come and throw down you
know my לחי lechi or my... my לחי? lechi? So מן דשדייה
מן, min de-shadyei min, throw it down for me? So שמע מינה
לא קיבלה מיניה. shema minah lo kiblah minei. You see that שמואל
Shmuel right did not accept this pushback because presumably what they're debating
is does this constitute a מבוי? maboi? Did it because presumably it
didn't have two courtyards? So שמואל Shmuel still went by his פסק.
psak. Yes I don't care, I'm still going to call it a
מבוי. maboi. So you see that שמואל Shmuel did not reverse his
position. So the גמרא Gemara says לא לעולם אימא לך קיבלה מיניה.
lo le-olam eima lach kiblah minei. Maybe שמואל Shmuel did accept the
pushback and he reversed his position and you do need two courtyards.
So therefore what was going on here? והכא
חזנא הוא דהוה אכיל נהמא בביתיה ואתי ביית בבית כנישתא. ve-hacha chazana
hu de-hava achil nahama be-veiteih ve-ati bayyet be-veit kenishta. The question was
here not whether there was one courtyard or two courtyards or whatever.
Here the point was maybe he agreed you needed two courtyards and
each courtyard needed two houses. The question was did you really have
here two houses? Why? Because there was a חזן chazan who you
know a sexton in the בית beis of the שול shul that
would eat bread in his home and he would sleep in a
house in the courtyard. And now we're back to the question of
does it go by where you eat or where you sleep and
is this considered to be a place of habitation? ואיבו בר איחי
סבר מקום פיתא גורם. ve-Eivu bar Ichi savar makom pita goreim. So
איבו בר איחי Eivu bar Ichi was of the opinion meaning he
now, meaning he held. He wasn't even a פוסק posek here, he
wasn't a רב. rav. But he thought that שמואל Shmuel right he
thought שמואל Shmuel was assuming this guy doesn't live here. This guy
lives where he eats. And he thought שמואל Shmuel was allowing it
even without two houses. But that's not really what was going on.
ושמואל לטעמיה דאמר מקום לינה גורם. ve-Shmuel le-taameih de-amar makom linah goreim.
He didn't understand שמואל's Shmuel פסק. psak. שמואל Shmuel said it's fine
make a לחי. lechi. So he figured oh look only one guy
lives here. שמואל Shmuel holds that it's enough to have one house,
one guy living, you don't need two people living. But he misunderstood.
שמואל Shmuel actually פסק'ד psak'd that way because he considered it as
if this חזן chazan actually lived in the courtyard. Okay so with
this way the גמרא Gemara nicely circles back to that other debate
of do you go where you eat or where you live and
is seeming to say that even שמואל Shmuel in the end reversed
himself and said you need two courtyards and two houses.
Yes? I'm terribly sorry.
Why are rabbis throwing down לחיס? lechis?
Yeah it's strange
on a theoretical,
not theoretical on a halachic position.
Okay but the
to destroy somebody else's property and not talk them through it and
not expressing opinions but the fact that they feel they have a
right to destroy someone's property which we see in the today all
the time.
Right, I yeah
you're
right I can't justify it. No I can't justify it.
Rabbis who are doing it.
Right and anyway it's like you know I mean I mean and
also I mean also like you would think it's also just a
כבוד הרב kevod ha-rav issue to שמואל. Shmuel. If רבנא's Rabana got
a problem go talk to שמואל Shmuel about it. You know maybe
he didn't maybe he didn't realize that this guy got a פסק
psak from שמואל. Shmuel. But whatever it was right.
I'm just having a tantrum.
Right I mean I would say look I'm not defending them but
there's an aspect here about the public... Nature of these things different
than somewhat other areas of פסק, psak, you know, which might be
a little bit what's sort of, you know, instigating them to act.
Oh, he's doing this, other people are going to do it, whatever.
But I understand that can justify a lot of violence and, you
know, and precedence. Right. I,
yeah, I totally, you know, I totally hear that. Who was the
first?
There was someone before. Oh, when they, the clash of חברון, Chevron,
it was nothing constantly until they made it a big formal issue.
That's interesting. And then they couldn't knock it down,
and that affected, you know, this whole thing. Right.
Well, constantly.
Really? Well, go, you were going to come to the defense here.
No. Okay. Well, I was just saying
because I was thinking דווקא davka of that. I was just going
to say that the whole nature of this is a הכר, heker,
right? The הלכה halacha is not... it's just a הכר. heker. Right.
So it serves as an announcement to the public that it's okay
to carry here, and he felt that it's an invalid announcement.
Nonetheless, you know, then I thought about the clash of חברון. Chevron.
Oh, this is... yes.
Who was the original? What?
Who was that before?
Remember they were knocking it down?
There was a whole thing.
I'm sorry, one more time.
The knocking it down.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, I know. Okay. Anyway, fine.
Okay. Let's take a look.
Okay, so we go on. So, right, by the way, if it
wasn't clear, meaning he slept outside... I don't know if I said
this correctly, but I'll just repeat it. He slept in a different
place outside of this מבוי mavoi courtyard, whatever. I'm sorry, no, he
ate in his own home outside of this מבוי mavoi courtyard, but
he slept in the בית כנסת, Beit Knesset, and the בית כנסת
Beit Knesset was in this מבוי mavoi and courtyard. So this person
אביי Abaye thought that since he didn't eat here, he ate in
his own home, he's not like he lives here, and שמואל Shmuel
held since he slept in the שול, shul, it is like he
lives in the שול. shul. Did שמואל Shmuel ever reverse his position?
So שמואל Shmuel might have reversed his position, but he considered it
like there were two people who lived in this courtyard because one
of them slept in the שול, shul, and that was enough even
though he ate somewhere else. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: מבוי שצידו אחד
עובד כוכבים וצידו אחד ישראל. Mavoi she-tzido echad oved kochavim ve-tzido echad
Yisrael. Okay, so now you've got a מבוי mavoi that one side
of it is... Rashi's got this nice picture. Okay, one side of
the מבוי mavoi is... Do people see the picture in רש״י? Rashi?
I'll show it on the board. Okay,
your מבוי mavoi is your alleyway, and one חצר chatzer here, one
חצר chatzer is the נכרי, nochri, okay, and the other one here
has, you know, all of these have Jews living in it.
Okay. So, now...
wait a minute. So... where are we?
וצידו אחד ישראל. ve-tzido echad Yisrael. אין מערבין אותו דרך חלונות להתירו
דרך פתחים למבוי. Ein me'arvin oto derech chalonot le-hatiro derech petachim la-mavoi.
So what can't you do? So he says... let me just hold
on double-check רש״י Rashi again. Wait
a minute,
right.
So basically,
so you have here this מבוי mavoi opens up into a רשות
הרבים. reshut ha-rabim.
Okay, and these חצרות chatzerot open up one into the other. And
from this last חצר, chatzer, you can get into the מבוי, mavoi,
very complicated. Okay, so what you want to do is, here's the
question: Can all of these guys make an עירוב eruv amongst themselves,
okay, which means that you can carry from all of this, and
because now they made an עירוב eruv amongst themselves, they're one
unit, can they carry now into the street? Okay, because then is
it... so that gets all questions about like is it ישראל אחד,
Yisrael echad, you know, דר dar with a נכרי, nochri, and so
on. So let's take a look. So he says, so he says...
let's read it again. וצידו אחד ישראל. ve-tzido echad Yisrael. אין מערבין
אותו דרך חלונות. Ein me'arvin oto derech chalonot.
So if they have these windows between, you know... Oh, I'm sorry,
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
You have
one courtyard here, okay, and you have houses that are somehow or
whatever.
So I mean it's the same point, but it's just that they're
houses rather than that we're talking חצר chatzer about דרך חלונות. derech
chalonot. Okay, so they can have the windows can open up from
one house to the other. Okay. So how do they go? Yeah,
how do they go in the courtyard? I don't know, maybe there's
like, you know, some space in front of the houses, not between
the houses or something. Okay, so it's basically same idea, same idea
except it's one courtyard here. So now they all have a shared
front yard. It's attached houses with a shared front yard, okay? That's
the issue. So...
This diagram here is pretty different than that.
It is?
רש״י Rashi
has the houses you have to stack vertically, it has them horizontally.
No, it's just... well, that's different. Just turn your page.
But they all open into רשות הרבים. reshut ha-rabim.
Yeah. And רש״י Rashi has one as a חצר. chatzer. Yeah, רש״י
Rashi has this last one as a חצר. chatzer. Yeah. I sort
of have it that they opened up into the side. All right,
so let's take a look though.
Okay, so let's read again. בציור הח׳ אין מערבין אותו דרך חלונות
להתיר דרך פתחים למבוי. B'tziyur ha-chet ein m'arvin oso derech chalonos l'hatir
derech p'tachim l'mavoi. So you cannot go ahead and make
an עירוב eruv amongst these houses, you have to, just one second,
one minute.
One
minute, just one minute.
Just one second. All right, so anyway, so what's the point? So
he says you cannot go ahead and make an עירוב eruv amongst
these houses in order to go ahead and say we're going now
carry into, you know, we're not going to carry into this into
this מבוי. mavoi. So why not? Let's take a look. Let's read
a little bit more, the גמרא Gemara will explain it. Okay, so
אין מערבין אותו דרך חלונות להתיר דרך פתחים למבוי. ein m'arvin oso
derech chalonos l'hatir derech p'tachim l'mavoi. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף אמר
רב אפילו בחצר. Amar lei Abaye l'Rav Yosef amar Rav afilu b'chatzer.
Would he say this even if this was not a מבוי mavoi
here between them, but this was a חצר chatzer between them? So
אמר ליה amar lei אין, in, he said yes. דאי לאו אמר
מאי הוה אמינא, De-i lav amar mai hava amina, because if he
wouldn't have said this, meaning what would I have thought? Why would
I have thought and this now will explain it that there might
be a difference between a מבוי mavoi and a חצר? chatzer? What
would I have thought was going on here? Here's what I would
have thought.
מאי הוה אמינא? Mai hava amina? טעמא דרב משום דקסבר אין מבוי
ניתר בלחי וקורה Ta'ama d'Rav mishum d'kasavar ein mavoi nitar b'lechi v'kora
עד בתים וחצרות פתוחים לתוכו. ad batim v'chatzeros p'tuchim l'socho. So I
would have thought that the reason if it was just about a
מבוי, mavoi, I think this is not correct, but anyway this is
one this is one חצר, chatzer, a big חצר chatzer with multiple
houses, okay? I'm just going to do it sort of my way
or whatever, okay? בית בית בית, bayit bayit bayit, but you have
windows. Okay, so this is basically... so I would have said the
reason רב Rav doesn't want them to make an עירוב, eruv, right,
is because as soon as they make an עירוב eruv essentially it
is a חצר chatzer with one בית, bayit, not with two בתים
batim and so on. So then you've got a problem about, you
know, about do you have two חצרות, chatzeros, that it's not a
חצר chatzer with... wait a minute, that doesn't make sense. I'm sorry.
I got confused here.
One minute. נכרי וישראל דרין בחצר אחת והוא אסור. Nochri v'Yisrael darin
b'chatzer achas v'hu asur.
One minute, one minute. Let's
look here. No, no, no. No, no, no. It's more simple than
that. It's that it's not considered a חצר chatzer because because where
the נכרי nochri is, is not considered... the נכרי nochri is not
a distinct חצר. chatzer. So if רב Rav had just said you
can't do this base, okay, you can't go ahead and do this
base and carry in and carry in the מבוי, mavoi, I would
have said the problem is just you can't allow the לחי lechi
or קורה kora because you really only have... it really has nothing
to do with these houses. It really has to do with the
fact that you only have one חצר, chatzer, because that חצר chatzer
doesn't count. All right, well that's a pretty complicated way to say
that, then he already said that you need two חצרות. chatzeros. So
why would I have thought that he had to say this again?
טרתי למה לי? Tarti lama li? If that was the whole point
of that פסק, psak, just to say you need two חצרות chatzeros
and that a נכרי׳ס nochri's being in a חצר chatzer and the
other side doesn't count, why a... you know, why go and say
this the whole time? צריכא. Tzricha. No, you need to tell it
twice. דאי מההיא הוה אמינא דירת עובד כוכבים שמה דירה. De-i me-hahi
hava amina diras oved kochavim shema dira. If you just said you
need two חצרות, chatzeros, I would have said, okay, but if a
נכרי nochri lives in one of the חצרות, chatzeros, it's still called
a חצר chatzer for this purpose. קא משמע לן דדירת עובד כוכבים
לא שמה דירה. Ka mashma lan d'diras oved kochavim lo shema dira.
So he's telling us this case, again it's sort of complicated there
talking about houses and windows, but ultimately he's telling you this case
to tell you that חצר chatzer isn't a חצר chatzer because a
נכרי nochri is living in it. So just tell us this הלכה.
halacha. ואי מהא הוה אמינא לא ידענא בתים כמה. V'ei mei-ha hava
amina lo yadana batim kama.
I wouldn't have known how many houses make up a חצר. chatzer.
קא משמע לן בתים תרין. Ka mashma lan batim terein. He says
you need two houses and two courtyards. Okay. So if he had
just said it by a מבוי, mavoi, I would have ignored whatever
he's trying to say here about the houses and the windows, and
I would have said that's simply just a פסק psak that you
need two חצרות, chatzeros, and this isn't a חצר chatzer because it's
a חצר chatzer of a נכרי. nochri. And that's how I would
have conceptualized the whole point of that. But if you're telling me
he's telling me even by a חצר, chatzer, right, it's not about
the לחי lechi issue. Okay, a חצר chatzer has walls and so,
it's not about the לחי lechi issue, so there's some other thing
that is going on here. So what's going on? So
therefore קא משמע לן השתא דאמר רב אפילו חצר. ka mashma lan
hashta d'amar Rav afilu chatzer. So what's the reason you can't do
this?
טעמא דרב דקסבר אסור לעשות יחיד במקום עובדי כוכבים. Ta'ama d'Rav d'kasavar
asur la'asos yachid bimkom ovdei kochavim. So here the problem is is
that if by... if you go ahead and that's a חצר, chatzer,
right, what do you have to do for the נכרי nochri who
lives
in...
If he's not,
because there's only one Jew, right? So what רבא Rava is saying
is, you figured, look, I'm going to solve the problem. We have
multiple Jews in this courtyard and the נכרי Nochri is in this
courtyard. Let's all make an עירוב Eiruv somehow like among ourselves, okay,
and ignore the נכרי Nochri I mean, if you could do that,
it would always work, essentially. Okay, but here but anyway, but here
the houses sort of open directly into one another. So maybe it's
better maybe that they open directly into one another, not through the
yard, we'll all essentially be one household and it'll be like a
יחיד במקום נכרי. yachid bimkom Nochri. Okay? And that's how you think
you're going to solve it.
You never said that before though.
I know. So let's take a look. So טעמא דרבא דקסבר אסור
לעשות יחיד במקום עובדי כוכבים. Taama deRava dekasavar assur la'asot yachid bimkom
ovdei kochavim. You can't do this. You can't turn yourself into a
יחיד, yachid, and maybe not as much of an עירוב Eiruv principle
as the reason they didn't want you to be together, a single
household with a non-Jew because of their fear concerns, but that's his
חידוש. chiddush. His חידוש chiddush is about you're trying to make this
one house, right, not even through the courtyard, just combining the attached
houses, that you are not allowed to do to solve this problem.
אמר רב יוסף אי הכי היינו דשמענא ליה לרב טבלא דאמר, Amar
Rav Yosef ihachi hainu deshamnan lei leRav Tavla deamar, ah, now I
understand it. I understand why רב טבלא Rav Tavla said this. He
said עובדי כוכבים עובדי כוכבים תרי זימני. ovdei kochavim ovdei kochavim trei
zimnei. He when he told over this teaching of רב, Rav, he
said where was the teaching? מבוי שצידו אחד עובדי כוכבים צידו אחד
ישראל אין מערבין אותו דרך חלונות לצורך דרך פתחים למבוי. Mavoi shetzido
echad ovdei kochavim tzido echad Yisrael ein mearvin oso derech chalonos letzorech
derech pesachim lemavoi.
So he actually said the word, you know, עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim
a second time in that teaching. רש"י Rashi has it, let's see
where רש"י Rashi says, השתא ודאי מפורשא מילתא דרב, Hashta vadai meforsha
milsa deRav,
אין מערבין אותו כולה. ein mearvin oso kulah. Anyway
he said this teaching, he said twice: you cannot do this with
a non-Jew. If there's a non-Jew on the other side, you can't
do this with a non-Jew. So I had no
idea, he
says, ולא ידנא מאי קאמר. velo yadana mai ko amar. I didn't
know why he was emphasizing non-Jew. And now I get why he's
emphasizing non-Jew. Because the point of the reason you're not allowed to
do this is because we don't want you to be basically a
single household together with the non-Jew. Okay, so that was a little
complicated, but in the end, the upshot was if it was by
a מבוי, mavoi, you would the issue is that you need שתי
חצרות. shtei chatzeros. If it's by a חצר, chatzer, the issue is
that although these houses are attached and you could consider them one
house, and therefore it would be a יחיד במקום נכרי, yachid bimkom
Nochri, which is when you don't have to worry about שכירות, sechirah,
but we don't want to allow you to become a יחיד במקום
נכרי yachid bimkom Nochri and that's why you're not allowed to do
it. And that's why at the end גמרא Gemara says he repeated
non-Jew many times multiple times when he was telling this over in
order to emphasize that that was the problem of יחיד במקום. yachid
bimkom.
Wait, wait, but getting back to what we actually...
we're ending. Let's pass it out.